Guide to the William W. L. Glenn Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William W. L. Glenn papers
1959-1993
MS 1693
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
(1 box)
The papers consist of correspondence and memoranda relating to William W. L. Glenn's career as a surgeon and member of the faculty of the Yale University School of Medicine. The papers focus on Glenn's work on the radio frequency diaphragm pacemaker and on his work as a member of the board of directors of the Charles E. Culpepper Foundation. William Wallace Lumpkin Glenn was born in Asheville, North Carolina on August 12, 1914. He received a B.S. degree from the University of South Carolina in 1934 and an M.D. degree from Jefferson Medical College of Philadelphia in 1938. Following appointments at the Harvard School of Public Health and the Jefferson Medical College of Philadelphia, Glenn joined the Cardiovascular Surgical Section of the Yale University School of Medicine in 1948 and served as its section chief from 1965-1975. Glenn was instrumental in the development of the first radio frequency diaphragm pacemaker and has written extensively on thoracic and cardiovascular surgery in general and cardiac pacemakers in particular. Glenn was named the Charles W. Ohse Professor Emeritus in 1985.
Glenn, William W. L.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William W. L. Glenn, 1995.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence and memoranda relating to William W. L. Glenn's career as a surgeon and member of the faculty of the Yale University School of Medicine. The papers focus on Glenn's work on the radio frequency diaphragm pacemaker and on his work as a member of the board of directors of the Charles E. Culpepper Foundation. William Wallace Lumpkin Glenn was born in Asheville, North Carolina on August 12, 1914. He received a B.S. degree from the University of South Carolina in 1934 and an M.D. degree from Jefferson Medical College of Philadelphia in 1938. Following appointments at the Harvard School of Public Health and the Jefferson Medical College of Philadelphia, Glenn joined the Cardiovascular Surgical Section of the Yale University School of Medicine in 1948 and served as its section chief from 1965-1975. Glenn was instrumental in the development of the first radio frequency diaphragm pacemaker and has written extensively on thoracic and cardiovascular surgery in general and cardiac pacemakers in particular. Glenn was named the Charles W. Ohse Professor Emeritus in 1985.
Cardiac pacemakers; Cardiology; Chest -- Surgery; Surgery -- Study and teaching; Glenn, William W. L.; Charles E. Culpeper Foundation; Yale University. Department of Surgery
- Additional Material, Accession 1995-M-151
  - Carter Center of Emory University [includes memo on a meeting with Jimmy Carter], 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Charles E. Culpepper Foundation, Inc.
    - Fellowship program [correspondence discussing establishment], 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Foundation grants [correspondence and other material concerning proposals], 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Lecture series in the history of medicine [correspondence concerning support], 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chinese delegation visit, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Curriculum vitae, Circa 1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Glenn Lecture, American Heart Association, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Radio frequency diaphragm pacemaker [correspondence and records of the first patient], 1966-1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Remote stimulation by radio frequency transmissions [grant proposals], 1959, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Soviet Cardiology Delegation visit [included Pavel Lukomskij], 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)